Taking it personal?
Personalize this!
You're listening to Higher Ed
Hot Takes, and I'm Joel Goodman.
When I took my second higher ed web job
in 2010, I remember my boss immediately
talking about personalization, though
I don't remember him using those words.
He was reading a book about the
power of Amazon showing you what
you should buy next, and Netflix's
ability to tailor content to you based
on what you had watched previously.
The desire to personalize has only
grown in our sector, but there's
still a lot of uncertainty around
what personalization should look like.
We started with mail merge features
in our emails, we moved on to accepted
student videos or landing pages customized
to the person's name, custom mailers
and digital view books that require
a lot of work from the student to
whittle down all of the information.
It's kind of exhausting to be honest,
and apart from email, --quick plug
for my friends' book, Mailed It!
--nothing has really moved the needle.
Most institutions don't even have
the proper infrastructure in place to
attribute traffic to records in their
CRM, but when they do, watch out.
Ask a higher ed marketer what
personalization should look like, and
you'll get a wide range of responses
from, I have no idea, to letting
people save settings on the homepage.
I'm sorry to tell you this, but
customizable homepages are a
waste of time, effort, and money.
No one comes back to your homepage.
And why would you want them to?
And I think this is part of the
issue with higher ed, we have to be
beaten over the head with something.
There's no sense of nuance.
If the fancy tech isn't obvious
enough, think you know, drone videos,
chatbots, those customizable homepages
again, it must not be working.
But when you think about how
personalization is supposed to
work, it's not flashing up a big
graphic with someone's name on it
and the list of all their attributes.
You don't do that, right?
Don't, that's creepy.
The only way personalization works
is through trying to be invisible.
That's my take on AI tools too.
All of this stuff is
supposed to be invisible.
It should feel like magic
or feel like nothing.
Personalization that works, guides
your visitors to take action in
the most natural ways possible.
But higher ed wants to be in their
faces because we spent the money on it.
We're gonna show how cool and forward
thinking and cutting edge we are.
How will they know we're
personalizing things for them if
we don't yell it in their faces?
And of course, we don't know
if it's working otherwise.
Nuance doesn't get the
president's attention.
Be honest.
That's why you buy AI chatbots and
these supposed AI CRO products.
They're fancy and new.
They make you look like
you're keeping up with tech.
The problem is that your
audience doesn't care.
They don't.
You're lucky if they even
make it to your website.
Your goal then should be to
make it as easy as possible
for them to take an action.
Don't distract them with popups and chat
bots and forms popping up everywhere.
You're meant to curate a
frictionless experience, but all
these tools do besides sucking your
budget dry is add more friction.
Is Teams suddenly a joy to use
now that Microsoft is shoehorned
CoPilot into every corner?
Have your personal interactions
with customer support chatbots
gotten any better in the past year?
Have you unsubscribed to more or
fewer emails in the past six months?
We have no chill because we don't
understand the underlying tenants of
personalization marketing, too few of us
really understand the basics of conversion
rate optimization and even fewer
understand the so-called AI tech that's
underneath most of the tools we use.
Look, a university website, today at
least, is not a consumer product, and the
tools you use are infrastructural even
though they want you to believe otherwise.
This is an old problem.
There are so many universities
that still have unbranded
intranets and student portals.
If the modern marketing software, you're
being hard-sold today isn't meant for
public consumption, those old enterprise
software applications definitely aren't.
Here's the nuance, and
it's gonna sound obvious.
Your audience doesn't know your job.
They don't know anything about the
products being pitched to you on
their personal college search journey.
They aren't wondering if you're
using Slate or HubSpot or
Element451 or any other CRM.
They don't even use that search product
you're spending five figures on.
These are high school students,
single parents, people looking to
switch from a day job doing sales
to a career running a business.
They're not higher ed professionals.
Stop letting the tool get in the way
of the outcome because results are
way more valuable than impressions.
Results are more valuable than engagement.
Results are everything.
And what gets results is invisibility.
When you can anticipate a need or a
question or an action and seamlessly
resolve it, that is when you win.
Not by bragging about how hip
you are with the newest, shiny
thing that they don't care about.
Instead of buying software and SaaS
tools that have cool demos, ask if that
cool demo is what your audience wants.
If you're unable to understand a website
visitor based on your CRM data and the
additional signals they generate by using
your web platforms, you're doing it wrong.
If you think that the best path is
tricking a visitor into giving you
their information with a gamified
interface, just so you can create
tailored content summaries for them,
you are setting yourself up for failure.
I am gonna suggest that focusing your
time and your money on fixing your user
experience, not covering it up with a
snake oil solution, will save you tons
of cash and generate huge returns.
I know this because I do it every
day in higher ed and I do it without
kickbacks from companies trying to
make as much money as they can off
of this industry before it fails.
I know I'm a bad capitalist, but
there's a huge technical knowledge
gap in our industry and companies
that sell AI powered tools have only
increased that through obfuscation.
They claim to be transparent
and benevolent while pocketing
your cash for smoke and mirrors.
The past three years have
generated so much slop.
It's harder than ever to pick out the
good from the bad, the truth from the
fibs, and the outcomes from the promises.
Stay vigilant, be a critic, not a skeptic.
I'm not sure American higher education
has ever been in a more critical
position, and in the UK the circumstances
are different, but also precarious.
Canada and Australia are also
seeing hard financial times.
I'm not convinced it's going to
get much easier, so make every
dollar, pound, or Euro count.
Thanks for listening.
Find me, Joel Goodman,
on LinkedIn or Bluesky.